Inventory of the Ernest Fred Easterbrook papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest Fred Easterbrook papers
1852-1988
2006C56
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 2 digital PDF files (9.1 linear feet, 0.005 GB)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, orders, reports, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to American military operations in the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II, military operations during the Korean War, American military assistance to Thailand, and American army aviation. Includes papers of Edmund Pepperell Easterbrook, army chaplain and father of E. F. Easterbrook. Transcribed copies of Earnest Fred Easterbrook's World War II diaries (10 March 1944 - 23 February 1945) are available at http://www.hoover.org/library-archives/collections or at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Easterbrook, Ernest Fred, 1908-1989.
Easterbrook, Edmund Pepperell, 1864-1933.
Access
Collection is open for research. Transcribed copies of Earnest Fred Easterbrook's World War II diaries (10 March 1944 - 23 February 1945) are available at http://www.hoover.org/library-archives/collections or at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Transcribed copies of Earnest Fred Easterbrook's World War II diaries (10 March 1944 - 23 February 1945) are available at http://www.hoover.org/library-archives/collections or at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Materials
Joseph Warren Stilwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1908 August 6 Born, Fort Worden, Washington, United States, to Edmund Pepperell Easterbrook and Fannie Luscombe
1931 B.S., Military Academy; Commander, Second Lieutenant, U.S. Army
1938 September 9 Married Nancy Stilwell, daughter of General Joseph Warren Stilwell
1943-1945 Stationed under General Joseph Warren Stilwell in China-Burma-India Theater
1945 Awarded Combat Infantry's Badge
1946 Awarded the Legion of Merit
1946-1949 Member, staff and faculty, U.S. Infantry School
1948 Awarded Bronze (First Oak-Leaf Cluster) Star Medal
1949-1951 Member, staff and faculty, Canadian Army Staff College
1953 Awarded the Silver Star
1954 Awarded the Legion of Merit
1954-1955 Member, staff and faculty, U.S. Command and General Staff College
1955-1957 Assigned, G-3, Allied Land Forces, Central Europe, SHAPE, Combat Infantry Badge; Military Cross 1st class (Belgium)
1957-1959 Director, army aviation, ODCSOPS, Department of Army
1959 475th Infantry Regiment, China-Burma-India (CBI); advanced through grades to Major General, U.S. Army
1959-1961 Commanding General, U.S. Army Aviation Center
1961-1963 Commanding General, 25th Infantry Division
1963-1965 Chief, Joint U.S. Military Advisory Group, Thailand
1965 Awarded the Distinguished Service Medal
1965-1967 Deputy Commanding General, Sixth U.S. Army
1967 Awarded La Croix de Guerre 1940 avec Palme and The Royal Honorable Flying Badge
1985 Author, The Soldier and the Cross
1989 February 19 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Ernest Fred Easterbrook document American military operations in the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II, U.S. Army operations in the Korean War, American military assistance to Thailand, and army aviation. Correspondence, orders, photographs, reports, speeches, and writings relate to Major General Easterbrook's tenure as an infantry instructor of Chinese troops in World War II, commander of the 7th Infantry regiment in Korea, and deputy commanding general of the 6th Army, headquartered at the Presidio in San Francisco.
In addition to documenting Easterbrook's career in the military, the collection includes the papers of his father, Edmund Pepperell Easterbrook (1864-1933), chief chaplain of the United States Army. Correspondence, reports, and photographs chronicle Edmund Easterbrook's career as a chaplain in Cuba during the Spanish-American war and Germany in World War I.
The collection includes two published biographies and related materials: The Soldier and the Cross (1985), a biography of Edmund Easterbrook written by Ernest Easterbrook, and The Soldier with a Heart (2006), a biography of Ernest Easterbrook written by his son, John Easterbrook.
World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; United States--Military relations--Thailand.; Thailand--Military relations--United States.; United States. Army--Aviation; United States. Army--Officers.; Chaplains, Military--United States
- Edmund Pepperell Easterbrook Papers, 1852-1978 (Boxes 1, 3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes citizenship papers, correspondence, clippings, commissions, reports, photographs, printed matter, and memorabilia relating to Edmund Easterbrook's life and his position as the chief chaplain of the United States Army. The series is further subdivided into Personal, Career, Photographs and Clippings files and then ordered chronologically.
  - Personal file, 1896-1933
    - Citizenship document, 1896 (Box-folder 1: 15)
      Includes signature, brochure, note, and picture of Rockton Church.
    - Fannie Easterbrook memorial service, 1929 (Box-folder 1: 24)
      Includes clippings and letters related to the death of Edmund Easterbrook's wife.
    - Biographical sketch and general information, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - Retirement and death, 1933 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Career file, 1899-1978
    - Commission, 1899 (Box-folder 1: 16)
      Appointment to chaplain, United States Army.
    - Spanish-American War, 1898-1955 (Box-folder 1: 17)
      Includes letters.
    - Chaplain's duties, 1899-1913, undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
      Printed matter and a letter.
    - Philippines, 1900-1918 (Box-folder 1: 19)
      Photographs and negatives.
    - Records from chaplain's school, 1902-1915 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Monthly reports, 1908, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
      Written while stationed in Manila.
    - Germany, Senior Chaplain of Armed Forces, 1919-1923 (Box-folder 3: 4)
      Clippings, pictures, and program for President Theodore Roosevelt's memorial service by Edmund Easterbrook. Includes a letter to Edmund Easterbrook conferring on him the Croix de Chevalier de la Légion d'Honneur by the President of the French Republic.
    - Chief Chaplain of the United States Army, 1928-1933 (Box-folder 1: 25)
      Clippings, letters, and printed matter relating to his retirement.
    - Fort Monroe, Virginia, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 27)
      A plaque honoring the memory of Army Chaplain Edmund Easterbrook dedicated in Memorial Day services at Fort Worden.
  - Photographs, 1852-1973
    - Family portraits, 1852-1911 (Box-folder 1: 13)
      Includes photographs from Easterbrook's childhood in England.
    - Family portraits, 1891-1973 (Box-folder 1: 29)
      Includes pictures from Fort Worden, Thanksgiving service in Ramblon, Rhode Island, notes, postcard, and souvenirs from the Holy Lands.
    - Family portraits before and after World War I, 1906-1916, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 1: 22-23)
    - Headshots of Edmund Easterbrook, 1909, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
      Includes service reports.
  - Clippings, 1932
    - Philippines, 1932 (Box-folder 1: 20)
- Ernest Fred Easterbrook Papers, 1903-2006 (Boxes 1-22)
  Includes correspondence, journals, clippings, medical reports, flight records, photographs, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and printed matter relating to Ernest Easterbook's career in the United States Army. The series is further subdivided into Personal, Career, Correspondence, Photographs, Speeches, Writings, Certificates, Awards, Clippings, and Printed Matter files and then ordered chronologically.
  - Personal file, 1903-1983
    - 1903-1977 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1922-1970, undated (Box-folder 16: 4)
      Includes article about movies shown by Edmund Easterbrook, article titled "Reminiscences," certificate from the Church of the Centurion, clippings, invitation, letters, program for armistice day service, and four unidentified pictures.
    - 1957-1967 (Box-folder 8: 11)
      Includes medical report.
    - 1958 (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 14: 1-6)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 15: 1-10)
    - Journal, circa 1960s (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Passports, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      Includes two photographs and cancelled passports.
    - China trip, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 2: 8)
      Includes article, journal, and notes.
  - Career file, 1936-1986
    - Efficiency reports, 1932-1965 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Infantry school, 1933-1966 (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Includes United States Military Advisory Group to the Republic of Korea, National Defense College, National War College, and Academic Department telephone directory.
    - Panama, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 18: 5)
      Letters, list of assignments of men of details in fields, memoranda, printed matter, and special orders, including from War Department.
    - Camp Dix, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 18: 6)
      Commendation for his lecture on the Panama Canal before the Reserve Officers Association, letters, and special orders issued by the War Department.
    - War Department efficiency report and special orders, 1937-1942 (Box-folder 18: 11)
    - Special orders, 1941 (Box-folder 17: 6)
      Relieved from duty by Adjutant General.
    - Diaries, notebooks, and records of army personnel, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      Includes clippings, card signed by Ernest Easterbrook, messages, and miscellany.
    - China-Burma-India Theater, 1943-1987
      - General information, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
      - 475th Infantry Association (CO CT 475), 1944 and undated (Box-folder 12: 1)
        Lists of addresses, ammunition, weapons, and accessories to be carried by mules.
      - 475th Infantry, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 11: 3)
        Includes general orders, letters, memoranda, printed matter, and roster of officers and home addresses. See oversize boxes for maps and other materials.
      - Merrill's Marauders, 1968-1987 (Box-folder 10: 6-8)
        Includes brochure, clippings, correspondence, lists, memoranda, printed matter, and related materials.
    - Fort Benning, Georgia, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      Includes a pictorial report of the conference, list of army personnel, memoranda from John W. O' Daniel in appreciation of Ernest Easterbrook's outstanding work as Secretary of the Infantry Conference, Infantry School.
    - Sketch of "A" CO BUNC Combat Patrol, undated (Box-folder 12: 5)
      See oversize boxes for magazine, maps, and other materials.
    - Canada, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 18: 2)
      Letter, nominal roll and address list, National Defense College and Canadian Army Staff College, and a poem.
    - Miscellany, 1952-1989 (Box-folder 12: 2-3)
      Includes award, card, certificate citation, clippings, correspondence, list of officers and casualties, memoranda, newsletters, notes, printed mattter, roster, and special orders
    - Roster of officers and enlisted men of Korean Military Advisory Group (KMAG) RTC #1, 29th ROK Infantry Division, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      Includes personnel roster from Department III, clippings, memoranda in appreciation of Ernest Easterbrook's completion of duty with the Command and General Staff College and promotion to General Officer for his outstanding service as Director, Department III.
    - France, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 18: 9)
      Clippings, award of Croix de Guerre, article on Ernest Easterbrook, and a Christmas letter.
    - Flight records, 1958-1967 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - Briefings, 1959, undated (Box-folder 17: 5)
      Includes notes.
    - Miscellany, 1959-1986 (Box-folder 13: 11)
      Correspondence, letter of recommendation for promotion to Major General, magazines, and printed matter.
    - Clearance record, list of papers, and telegrams, 1962 (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - Thailand, 1963-1965
      - Order regarding Ernest Easterbrook's assignment of command of Joint United States Military Advisory Group (JUSMAG) to Thailand, APO 146, San Francisco, California, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - Scrapbooks, 1963 June-November, 1965 April-August (Box 22)
      - Joint United States Military Advisory Group (JUSMAG), Thailand, 2 scrapbooks, 1963 November - 1965 April (Box 21)
      - Printed matter and correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - Certificate, memorandum, notes, press release and rosters, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 9: 7)
      - Embassy of the United States of America, Bangkok, and Thailand telephone directories, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 4: 10)
        Includes American Women's Club of Thailand directory.
      - Alphabetical roster, Joint United States Military Advisory Group (JUSMAG) to Thailand, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 5)
      - Proposal for East Asia International University, undated (Box-folder 8: 6)
      - Albums, compliments of RTA Cavalry Center, Sarabury, Thailand. From Sawad-Di to Major General Easterbrook with the best wishes of the members of Army Section of Joint United States Military Advisory Group (JUSMAG) to Thailand, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Rosters, 6th Army, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - Scrapbook presented to Ernest Easterbrook by the 6th Army senior staff, undated (Box 20)
    - Fort Rucker, Alabama, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 13: 8-9)
      Includes certificate, correspondence, farewell message, magazines, newsletters, notes, and miscellany.
    - Retirement papers, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Retirement and letters of good wishes, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Retirement ceremony schedule and standard pilot log book, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1988
    - 1921-1932 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    - 1925-1927 (Box-folder 16: 3)
    - 1927-1930 (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - 1928 (Box-folder 16: 2)
      Includes clipping and diary.
    - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 7: 9-10)
    - 1962-1964 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
    - 1959-1962 (Box-folder 13: 1-7)
    - 1962-1964 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - 1963-1964 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 10: 2-4)
    - 1965 January-August (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    - Chief Joint United States Military Advisory Group (JUSMAG), Thailand, 1965 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 8: 1-4)
    - 1967 January-May (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - 1967 May-August (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 18: 7)
      Proposal for an Oral History Project. Correspondence with Glenn Campbell, Hoover Institution, Stanford University, and Willa Baum, University of California, Berkeley.
    - John H. Lattin Associates correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Photographs, 1918-1963
    - Boyhood pictures, brochure and proposal, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Plebe Year and at West Point, 1927-1930 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - As young officer at West Point and in Panama, including his wedding picture, 1935-1942 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Fort Benning, Georgia, 1948, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
      Faculty of Infantry School, Ernest Easterbrook with his family.
    - Canadian Army Staff College, 2 group pictures, 1949 January 19, 1950 January 16 (Box 20)
    - Pictures of Ernest Easterbrook and others taken in Korea, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - France, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Presidio of San Francisco, pre-arrival of 6th Army, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Ernest Easterbrook in army uniform and at social gathering, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Ernest Easterbrook including in Rucker, Alabama, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Ernest Easterbrook and his wife with others, 25th Division, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Ernest Easterbrook scrapbook, 1963 March-June, undated (Box 20)
      Includes 2 pictures of Ernest Easterbrook with unidentified individuals.
    - Thailand, army helicopters and reconnaissance helicopters, 1965, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Speeches, 1959-1967
    - 1959-1962 (Box-folder 17: 3)
      Includes brochure and clippings.
    - 1961-1967 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - AUSA dinner meeting, 1965 November 11 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Army ROTC graduates, 1966 January 27 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Fort Rucker, Alabama, 1966 March 1 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - The Soldier and the Cross, 1895-2006
    - The Soldier and the Cross: A Biography of My Father, Edmund P. Easterbrook, by Ernest F. Easterbrook, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - The Soldier and the Cross: A Biography of My Father, Edmund Easterbrook, and The Soldier with a Heart, biography of Ernest Easterbrook by John Easterbrook, 1985, 2006 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - Photographs used in The Soldier and the Cross, 1895-1929
      - Chapter 1, Edmund Easterbrook and his family and personalized souvenir from the Holy Lands, 1895-1897 and undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
      - Chapter 2, Edmund Easterbrook's family and his trips to Egypt and Palestine, 1897-1900 (Box-folder 1: 2)
        Includes acceptance of his commission as chaplain of the U.S. Army and memorandum from the office of the Adjutant General with instructions about his assignment.
      - Chapter 3, Chaplain from Manila, 1901 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      - Chapter 4, Chaplain and his work, 1902 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      - Chapter 5, Picture of Fort Worden, circa 1912 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      - Chapter 6, Individual reports of the chaplain to the Adjutant General, 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1: 6)
      - Chapter 7, Edmund Easterbrook and flag presentation at Fort Worden, 1918 and undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - Chapter 8, Pictures of Church of the Palace, reception for Commander Eva Booth, ceremony for awarding Légion d'Honneur, Edmund Easterbrook and his sons, wedding of Gladys Easterbrook, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Chapter 9, Pictures and negatives, Easter Sunrise Service at Walter Reed Hospital, appointment of Edmund Easterbrook as Chief of Chaplain, and Edmund Easterbrook's letter to Gladys Easterbrook, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - Chapter 10, Fort Worden, Memorial Day services, circa 1912, and visit to West Point, 1929 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1931-1989
    - Fort Benning, Georgia, 1931-1933, undated (Box-folder 18: 10)
      Certificate for the completion of a base course, Troops Schools, in the subject of care of animals, clippings, letters, notebook, orders from the War Department.
    - Recognitions received by Ernest Easterbrook from China, Korea, and Thailand, 1931-1954 (Box 19)
      - Diploma awarded for advancement in the Army of the United States, given at West Point, New York, 1931 June 11 (Box 19)
      - Letter of thanks from Headman of district office, Southern Cheju, Korea, for his help with the war orphans, 1954 February 23 (Box 19)
      - Testament from Korea for service to war orphans, 1954 March 3 (Box 19)
      - Letter of appreciation for his cooperation and maintenance of close liaison with the Advisory Group of 29th Infantry ROK Division and for his efforts in supplementing training aids, 1954 March 3 (Box 19)
      - Certificates of appreciation, 1954 (Box 19)
      - Testimonial for distinguished services in the reconstruction of educational and welfare institutions in Cheju, Korea, 1954 April (Box 19)
      - Testimonial in recognition of outstanding contribution to the administrative efforts at the orphanage of Chun-Sa, Korea, 1954 (Box 19)
      - Certificate of appreciation on the eve of his departure from Korea, undated (Box 19)
      - Album of pictures from Korea with illustrations in both Chinese and Korean, undated (Box 19)
    - Certificate for a diploma awarded to Ernest Easterbrook for graduating from the Defense Committee Course of Mediation, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1948 December (Box 22)
    - Memorial resolution of the California State Assembly in memory of the passing of Ernest Easterbrook, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Awards, 1908-1984
    - 1908-1984 (Box 20)
    - Awards of the Silver Star, citation for the Legion of Merit (Oak-Leaf Cluster), award of the Bronze Star Medal, and employment record, 1950-1963 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Clippings, 1908-1982
    - Fort Worden, 1908-1975 (Box-folder 1: 21)
      Includes printed matter and an article of remembrance of Ernest Easterbrook, Burman News.
    - Fort Rucker, Alabama, 1959 (Box-folder 17: 4)
      Clippings relating to Ernest Easterbrook's arrival as Commander of the U.S. Army Aviation Center.
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Hawaii, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Presidio of San Francisco, 1963-1966, undated (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - "Training on the Roof of the World," Ernest Easterbrook's article on Tibet in Army, 1982 (Box-folder 18: 8)
      Includes clippings, Joseph Warren's comments about the United States Army, correspondence, and map. Also includes typescript copies of the article.
  - Printed matter, 1954-1965
    - Front Line: The Third Infantry Division, Korean edition, 1954 October (Box 21)
    - Bangkok World, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - VIP Forecast, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Diary transcriptions
    The transcribed copies of Earnest Fred Easterbrook's World War II diaries (10 March 1944 - 23 February 1945) cover a significant period of his service during World War II. In 1942, Earnest Fred Easterbrook was assigned to the China-Burma-India (CBI) Theater (then commanded by Lieutenant General Joseph W. Stilwell); initially he was an instructor and head of department at Ramgarh, India, instructing Chinese soldiers and officers in military tactics and associated subjects. In early 1944, when these diaries begin, he was assigned to be General Stilwell's executive assistant in Burma. He continued in that position through the capture of Myitkyina; in late 1944, he was assigned to command the 475th Infantry Regiment, a component of the MARS Task Force, at that time the only US ground combat unit in the CBI Theater. In that capacity he led the regiment behind Japanese lines to cut the Burma Road in support of Chinese troops from Burma linking up with the Chinese Y-Force. The Y-Force was a 72,000-man force based in China's Yunnan Province that was forcing the Japanese out of southwestern China so that a land supply route - the soon to be named Stilwell Road from Ledo in India to Kunming in China - could be reopened.
    The diaries are significant for their detailed recording of the activity of Chinese units in northern Burma, including hand-drawn maps; as such, they are a companion to the Stilwell Diaries of the same period. In addition, during Easterbrook's command of the 475th Infantry Regiment, the diaries provide visibility to activities and personnel during that little-know part of the campaign in Burma. In the diaries, references to "dad" or "pop" are to General Stilwell. Easterbrook also refers to General Stilwell at times as "Q.B.," short for Quarterback, Stilwell's code name.